CONTACT

503-998-7444

7 /franco-ortega

in /francoortega

https://francoortega.com

PROFILE

Diligent and empathetic software engineer who thrives in collaborative, agile environments and loves to create user-focused products. Experienced in building internal tools, improving existing systems, developing new features, writing documentation, and debugging issues across the stack in business applications. Guided by optimism to dream big and balanced with practicality to ensure that goals are brought to fruition.

TECH AND TOOLS

JavaScriptNode

• TypeScript • Express

• HTML / CSS • GraphQL

ReactPostgreSQL

• Redux • pgAdmin

NextJSMongoDB

SassCompass

FigmaAirtable

MiroGit

• Storybook • GitHub

• JIRA • Heroku

JestNetlify

• QUnit • Postman

• Supertest • Zapier

React Testing Library

EDUCATION

Alchemy Code Lab

Software Engineering (2020–2021)

Michigan State University

Telecommunications (BA) Graduated with Honors (1996-2000)

FRANCO ORTEGA

FULL STACK SOFTWARE ENGINEER

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Software Engineer - Allocations (2021 - 2022)

Improved existing systems and built internal tools to automate manual workflows. Fulfilled technical requests and fixed bugs reported by customer-facing teams. Created documentation for technical and non-technical teams. Accomplishments:

- Added design system components, error handling, and styling to the React UI and refined the GraphQL query of a new tool to move items between users.
- Leveraged CSS to provide UI fixes without altering the existing architecture.
- Paired with a teammate to build a NextJS auth modal and user profile form.
- Created scripts to recover and validate missing data by querying internal Airtable and MongoDB databases, and an external document service.
- Documented how to distinguish between and address two separate issues that both appeared to yield the same error of PDFs failing to load.
- Developed & iterated processes to improve workflows at a fast-growing startup. This position was eliminated during a major company-wide downsize.

Driver - Radio Cab (2008–2020)

Provided safe, efficient rides by communicating clearly with customers from all walks of life while navigating ambiguity across a continuously changing landscape.

Substitute Paraeducator - Portland Public Schools (2003–2011)

Assisted with the care and education of special needs students.

TEAM PROJECTS

beHuman | <u>GitHub</u> - <u>VSCode Extension</u>

HTML | CSS | JavaScript | Node | Express | PostreSQL | Supertest | Heroku Tracks time and reminds users to take breaks via popups with wellness tips. My efforts included the time-tracking logic, tested endpoints with a data model and corresponding database table, and leading the development of an admin site.

ebb | <u>GitHub</u> - <u>Chrome Extension</u>

HTML | CSS | JavaScript | Chrome API

Reduces on-screen movement to improve accessibility for users with sensory conditions. I removed GIFs from view, paused CSS animations, injected the code into the browser, and implemented styling provided by our designer.

WeatherBeats | GitHub - Website

React | CSS | Node | Express | WeatherBit API | Spotify API | Heroku | Netlify Generates music playlists based on local weather with customization options. I acquired location data, built fetch requests, implemented a responsive design, and refactored components to enhance efficiency and modularity.

VOLUNTEER WORK

Ada Developers Academy (2022 - current)

One-on-one tutoring and study hall assistance for code school students.

Independent Publishing Resource Center (2017–2022)

Guided and assisted members using the facility to create art prints and zines.

Portland Zine Symposium (2003–2006; 2016–2020)

Provided bookkeeping and event planning for this annual small publisher festival.